[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Who was the father of Lord Rama?",
        "choices": [
            "King Dasaratha",
            "King Janaka",
            "King Bharata",
            "King Ravana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "King Dasaratha"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "What was the name of Lord Rama's kingdom?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhya",
            "Mithila",
            "Lanka",
            "Hastinapura"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ayodhya"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Who was Lord Rama's wife?",
        "choices": [
            "Sita",
            "Urmila",
            "Mandavi",
            "Shrutakirti"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sita"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Who was the author of the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Valmiki",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Nārada Muni",
            "Brahma deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Valmiki"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "What was the name of the river by which Rishi Valmiki's ashram was located?",
        "choices": [
            "Sarayu",
            "Tamasā",
            "Gangā",
            "Yamuna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tamasā"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "What was the name of the meter used to compose both the Ramayana and the Mahabharata?",
        "choices": [
            "Anustup",
            "Gayatri",
            "Trishtubh",
            "Jagati"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Anustup"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Who prompted Rishi Valmiki to narrate the life of Rama?",
        "choices": [
            "Nārada Muni",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "What were the names of the two disciples who recited the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "Lava and Kusha",
            "Bharata and Shatrughna",
            "Rama and Lakshmana",
            "Vāli and Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lava and Kusha"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "What is the meaning of the name Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "A furrow",
            "A lotus",
            "A river",
            "A star"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A furrow"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Who was the progenitor of Ikshvāku dynasty?",
        "choices": [
            "Ikshvāku",
            "Sagar",
            "Raghu",
            "Manu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ikshvāku"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Who is credited with bringing river Gangā to Earth?",
        "choices": [
            "Dasharatha",
            "Sagar",
            "Bhageeratha",
            "Dilip"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Bhageeratha"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "What is the name of Surya’s lineage, or the Solar dynasty?",
        "choices": [
            "Surya vamsha",
            "Chandra vamsha",
            "Ikshvāku vamsha",
            "Raghu vamsha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Surya vamsha"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "What is the name of the dynasty in which King Janaka was born?",
        "choices": [
            "Ikshvāku vamsha",
            "Raghu vamsha",
            "Nimi lineage",
            "Chandra vamsha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Nimi lineage"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Who was the father of Ravana?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Pulastya",
            "Rishi Vishrava",
            "Sukesh",
            "Sumāli"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vishrava"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Which god gave Rāvana the Pushpak vimān?",
        "choices": [
            "Shiva",
            "Vishnu",
            "Indra",
            "Brahma deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "What were the names of Rāvana’s three powerful sons?",
        "choices": [
            "Malyavan, Sumali and Mali",
            "Dashagreeva, Kumbhakarna and Vibhishana",
            "Kumbha, Nikumbha and Meghanad",
            "Rāvana, Kumbhakarna and Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kumbha, Nikumbha and Meghanad"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "What is the name of the condition that is similar to Kumbhakarna’s character in the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "Klein-Levin syndrome",
            "Down syndrome",
            "Tourette’s syndrome",
            "Autism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Klein-Levin syndrome"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "What were the names of the two sons of Rāvana born to Mandodari?",
        "choices": [
            "Indrajeet and Aksh",
            "Kumbha and Nikumbha",
            "Meghanad and Aksh",
            "Kumbhakarna and Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Meghanad and Aksh"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "What was the name of Rāvana's sister?",
        "choices": [
            "Tārā",
            "Rumā",
            "Shurpanakhā",
            "Kaikasi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shurpanakhā"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Who was the king of vānara tribe in Kishkindha before Sugreeva?",
        "choices": [
            "Riksharāja",
            "Vāli",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vāli"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Who was Vāli's wife?",
        "choices": [
            "Rumā",
            "Anjanā",
            "Tārā",
            "Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tārā"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "According to the document, what does the word ‘Ārya’ mean?",
        "choices": [
            "A race of people",
            "A gentlemanly quality",
            "A civilised person",
            "A person from Europe"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A gentlemanly quality"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "What was the width of Ayodhya, as mentioned in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "3 yojanas",
            "12 yojanas",
            "10 yojanas",
            "6000 sq km"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "3 yojanas"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "What was the length of Ayodhya, as mentioned in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "3 yojanas",
            "12 yojanas",
            "10 yojanas",
            "6000 sq km"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "12 yojanas"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Who is considered a saintly king according to the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Manu",
            "Rāma",
            "Dasharatha",
            "Bharata"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Dasharatha"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Who designed the city of Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "Vishvakarmā",
            "Shilpa",
            "Indra",
            "Kuber"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vishvakarmā"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "What is the meaning of the word Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "One who makes the world cry",
            "One who is a great warrior",
            "One who is a great king",
            "One who is a scholar of Vedas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "One who makes the world cry"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these is not a prominent city or place from the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "Mithilā",
            "Kekaya",
            "Hastinapur",
            "Panchavati"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hastinapur"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the name of the ashram of Rishi Vishvāmitra?",
        "choices": [
            "Siddhāshram",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Rishyamukha",
            "Panchavati"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Siddhāshram"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Who were the two rākshasas that were disrupting Vishvāmitra's yajña?",
        "choices": [
            "Māreecha and Subāhu",
            "Khara and Dushana",
            "Kumbha and Nikumbha",
            "Malyavan and Mali"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha and Subāhu"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "What was the name of the knowledge that Vishvāmitra gave to Rama and Lakshmana to make them impervious to hunger and fatigue?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahma Vidya",
            "Bala-Atibalā vidyā",
            "Agni Vidya",
            "Dhanurveda"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Bala-Atibalā vidyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Who was the rākshasi who used to live in the forest before Tātakā?",
        "choices": [
            "Simhikā",
            "Rambha",
            "Menakā",
            "Shurpanakhā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tātakā"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Which divine instrument did Rama use to kill Tātakā?",
        "choices": [
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Where did Vamana avatar live for many years as per the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhya",
            "Siddhāshram",
            "Mithilā",
            "Rishyamukha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Siddhāshram"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "What is the name of the bow of Shiva that was in the custody of King Janaka?",
        "choices": [
            "Shiva Dhanush",
            "Pināka",
            "Vijay",
            "Shiva shastra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shiva Dhanush"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "What is the term for valor or heroism as price?",
        "choices": [
            "Dhana shulka",
            "Rājya shulka",
            "Virya shulka",
            "Swayamvara"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Virya shulka"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Who is considered a Brahmarshi, as per the text?",
        "choices": [
            "A king with the attributes of a sage",
            "A sage who has realised Brahma, the ultimate truth",
            "A sage who controls all the senses",
            "A sage who performs rituals"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A sage who has realised Brahma, the ultimate truth"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "What was the name of the king who desired to go to heaven in his earthly body?",
        "choices": [
            "Trishanku",
            "Sagar",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Kaushika"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Trishanku"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "What was the name of the celestial nymph who distracted Kaushika’s intense austerities?",
        "choices": [
            "Rambha",
            "Menakā",
            "Urvashi",
            "Tilottama"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Menakā"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Who bestowed Brahmarshi-hood upon Kaushika?",
        "choices": [
            "Shiva",
            "Indra",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Vishnu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "What is the meaning of the word Unārya as mentioned in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "A race of people",
            "A person from Europe",
            "An uncivilised, deceitful, cowardly person",
            "A person from South India"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "An uncivilised, deceitful, cowardly person"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the colour of Rāma’s skin?",
        "choices": [
            "Fair",
            "White",
            "Dusky",
            "Golden"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Dusky"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "What is the name of the place where the Gangā emerges from the Himalayas and reaches Earth?",
        "choices": [
            "Gangotri",
            "Gomukh",
            "Devprayāg",
            "Rishikesh"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Gomukh"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Who does Rāma refer to as the one who is ‘नियमतः’?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaikasi",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Māreecha",
            "Seetā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Seetā"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "What was the name of the mantra that Rishi Agastya gave to Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Aditya Hridaya Stotra",
            "Gayatri Mantra",
            "Om Namah Shivaya",
            "Vishnu Mantra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Aditya Hridaya Stotra"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Who told Rāma about the location of Seetā in Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "Jatāyu",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Sampāti",
            "Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sampāti"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "What was the measurement of distance across the ocean that Hanumāna had to leap to reach Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "One hundred yojanas",
            "Three hundred yojanas",
            "A thousand yojanas",
            "A million yojanas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "One hundred yojanas"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Who was the chief queen of Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaikasi",
            "Tārā",
            "Mandodari",
            "Rumā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mandodari"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Who saved Rāma and Lakshmana when they were rendered unconscious by Indrajeet’s Brahmastra?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Garuda",
            "Vishnu",
            "Shiva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Garuda"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Who was the architect of the bridge made across the ocean to reach Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "Nala",
            "Neela",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Nala"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "What did Rāma give to Hanumāna to give to Seetā as a sign of his identity?",
        "choices": [
            "A bow",
            "A sword",
            "A ring",
            "A bracelet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A ring"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "What is the name of the forest in Lankā where Seetā was kept captive?",
        "choices": [
            "Dandakāranya",
            "Ashokavātikā",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Janasthāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ashokavātikā"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "What did Sugreeva give to Rāma to enable him to identify him easily?",
        "choices": [
            "A ring",
            "A garland made of Gaja pushpa",
            "A special bow",
            "A sword"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A garland made of Gaja pushpa"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "Who was Rāvana's son who captured and bound Hanumāna?",
        "choices": [
            "Aksh",
            "Kumbha",
            "Nikumbha",
            "Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Indrajeet"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Who intervened to save Hanumāna’s life when Rāvana ordered that he be killed?",
        "choices": [
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Mandodari"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vibhishana"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "What did Rāvana do to punish Hanumāna?",
        "choices": [
            "Killed him",
            "Imprisoned him",
            "Banished him",
            "Set fire to his tail and paraded him around Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Set fire to his tail and paraded him around Lankā"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "According to the text, whose mind was completely deluded?",
        "choices": [
            "Sugreeva",
            "Rāma",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "Who is credited with bringing the herbs from the Himalayas to save Rāma and Lakshmana from death?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Nala"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Who administered the herbs to Rāma and Lakshmana to restore them back to consciousness?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Sushena",
            "Vibhishana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sushena"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "What was the name of the weapon that struck Lakshmana, making him unconscious during the war with Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Pāshupatāstra",
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Shakti",
            "Agneyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shakti"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the meaning of the word 'sahadharmacharini'?",
        "choices": [
            "A friend",
            "A companion",
            "Equal partner in dharma",
            "A life partner"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Equal partner in dharma"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "What is the meaning of the term 'agni parikshā'?",
        "choices": [
            "A test of skill",
            "A test of strength",
            "A test of honesty",
            "A test by fire"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A test by fire"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "Which God vouched for Seetā’s purity after her agni parikshā?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Vishnu",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Agni deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Agni deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "According to the text, what does Rāma Rājya signify?",
        "choices": [
            "A kingdom ruled by the best king",
            "A peaceful and prosperous kingdom",
            "A kingdom where citizens are always happy",
            "A kingdom where the welfare of all citizens is paramount"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A kingdom where the welfare of all citizens is paramount"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "What are the names of the twin sons born to Seetā in Valmiki’s ashram?",
        "choices": [
            "Lava and Kusha",
            "Bharata and Shatrughna",
            "Rama and Lakshmana",
            "Vāli and Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lava and Kusha"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "What does the phrase ‘deva anugraha’ mean as used in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "God’s plan",
            "God’s design",
            "God’s grace",
            "God’s wish"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "God’s grace"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "According to the text, who is ‘Mahātejasvi’?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaikasi",
            "Anjanā",
            "Mandodari",
            "Pulastya’s wife"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Pulastya’s wife"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "question": "According to the text, which god granted the boon to Vāli which made him incredibly strong?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Vishnu",
            "Shiva",
            "None of the gods"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of the gods"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "question": "According to the text, who is ‘Yajnavalkya’?",
        "choices": [
            "A king",
            "A warrior",
            "A rishi",
            "A commander"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A rishi"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "question": "According to the text, who said to Rāvana, 'You are a sinner whose end is near'?",
        "choices": [
            "Sugreeva",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Shurpanakhā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vibhishana"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "question": "Which place does the text describe as the playground of Bhagvān Shankar?",
        "choices": [
            "Kailash",
            "Rishyamukha",
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kailash"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "question": "According to the text, who was referred to as ‘The one who made the world cry’?",
        "choices": [
            "Indrajeet",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Rāvana",
            "Vibhishana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "question": "What was the name of the mountain on which Lankā was located?",
        "choices": [
            "Trikuta",
            "Suvela",
            "Mahendra",
            "Rishyamukha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Trikuta"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "question": "Who is considered the most compassionate amongst the gods?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Vishnu",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Shiva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shiva"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "question": "Who told Rāma about his lineage?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Nārada Muni",
            "Bharata"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vashishtha"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "question": "What did Rāma describe as being like strands of straw?",
        "choices": [
            "Devas",
            "Asuras",
            "Human beings",
            "Rākshasas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Human beings"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "question": "What was the name of Sugreeva’s wife?",
        "choices": [
            "Tārā",
            "Rumā",
            "Anjanā",
            "Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rumā"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "question": "According to the text, who was married to Shurpanakhā?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāvana",
            "Vidyutjihvā",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Khara"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vidyutjihvā"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "question": "What does the text state about the lineage of Gautama Buddha?",
        "choices": [
            "He was from the Ikshvāku dynasty",
            "He was from the Surya vamsha",
            "He was from the Chandra vamsha",
            "He was an avatar of Vishnu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was a Suryavamshi, a descendant of Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "question": "Who was the mother of Lakshmana and Shatrughna?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaushalya",
            "Kaikeyi",
            "Sumitrā",
            "Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sumitrā"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "question": "What was the purpose for which Dasaratha conducted the Ashwamedha and Putreshti yajnas?",
        "choices": [
            "To have a grand celebration",
            "To increase his wealth",
            "To beget a successor",
            "To showcase his power"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To beget a successor"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "question": "What were the names of the two rakshasas who interrupted Vishvāmitra’s yajna?",
        "choices": [
            "Shurpanakhā and Indrajeet",
            "Khara and Dushana",
            "Māreecha and Subāhu",
            "Kumbha and Nikumbha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha and Subāhu"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "question": "Where did Rāma, Lakshmana and Vishvāmitra go after a successful yajna?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Mithilā",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mithilā"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "question": "What was the special condition for the marriage of Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "The suitor must win a battle",
            "The suitor must lift the Shiva Dhanush",
            "The suitor must have immense wealth",
            "The suitor must be the most learned"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The suitor must lift the Shiva Dhanush"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "question": "Who was the royal priest of Ayodhyā?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Nārada Muni"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vashishtha"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "question": "What was the name of the handmaiden who misled Kaikeyi about the coronation?",
        "choices": [
            "Urmila",
            "Manthara",
            "Sumitra",
            "Mandavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Manthara"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "question": "How many boons did Dasaratha grant to Kaikeyi?",
        "choices": [
            "One",
            "Two",
            "Three",
            "Four"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Two"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "question": "What was the first place of dwelling of Rāma, Seetā and Lakshmana after being banished?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Panchavati",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Dandakāranya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Chitrakoot"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "question": "Who directed Rāma, Seetā and Lakshmana to stay in Chitrakoot?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Bharadwaja",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Bharadwaja"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "question": "Where did Rāma, Seetā and Lakshmana spend most of their vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhya",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Dandakaranya",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Dandakaranya"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "question": "Who introduced Rāma to Jatāyu?",
        "choices": [
            "Sumantra",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Jatāyu himself"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Jatāyu himself"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "question": "Who disfigured Shurpanakha?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Rāvana",
            "Both Rāma and Lakshmana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lakshmana"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "question": "Who did Rāvana send to lure Seetā before abducting her?",
        "choices": [
            "Khara",
            "Dushana",
            "Māreecha",
            "Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "question": "What form did Māreecha take to lure Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "A golden deer",
            "A rishi",
            "A warrior",
            "A bird"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A golden deer"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "question": "Who was Jatāyu?",
        "choices": [
            "The king of vānaras",
            "A friend of Rāvana",
            "A friend of Dasaratha",
            "A rakshasa"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A friend of Dasaratha"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "question": "Which mountain were Sugreeva and his ministers hiding in?",
        "choices": [
            "Kailash",
            "Rishyamukha",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Mahendra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishyamukha"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "question": "What caused the misunderstanding about Vali’s death in Kishkindha?",
        "choices": [
            "An attack by Ravana",
            "A prophecy by a rishi",
            "A fight with Māyāvi",
            "A natural disaster"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A fight with Māyāvi"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "question": "Who took away Sugreeva’s wife, Rumā?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāvana",
            "Māyāvi",
            "Vāli",
            "Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vāli"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "question": "Who led Rāma and Lakshmana to Sugreeva in Kishkindha?",
        "choices": [
            "Jāmbavana",
            "Tārā",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Neela"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "question": "What was the name of Hanumāna's mother?",
        "choices": [
            "Tārā",
            "Anjanā",
            "Rumā",
            "Shabari"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Anjanā"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "question": "What did Sugreeva show Rāma which proved Seetā had been abducted?",
        "choices": [
            "Her jewelry",
            "A piece of her garment",
            "Her letter",
            "A note"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Her jewelry"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "question": "Who gave Rāma his ring to prove his credentials to Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "Bharata",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Rāma himself"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma himself"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "question": "Where did Hanumāna find Seetā in Lanka?",
        "choices": [
            "In Ravana’s palace",
            "In the forest",
            "In Ashokavātikā",
            "By the sea"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In Ashokavātikā"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "question": "Who offered to rescue Seetā and take her to Kishkindha right away?",
        "choices": [
            "Sugreeva",
            "Angada",
            "Jatāyu",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "question": "Why did Seetā refuse to be rescued and taken to Kishkindhā right away?",
        "choices": [
            "She wanted to wait for Rāma",
            "She didn't trust Hanumāna",
            "She was scared of Vāli",
            "She didn't want to leave Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "She wanted to wait for Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "question": "What did Hanumāna do to catch the attention of the rakshasas?",
        "choices": [
            "Ravaged the Ashoka forest",
            "Shouted loudly",
            "Started a fire",
            "Started fighting the soldiers"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ravaged the Ashoka forest"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "question": "Which powerful rakshasa caught Hanumāna?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāvana",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Prahasta"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Indrajeet"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "question": "What did Hanumāna do after his tail was set on fire?",
        "choices": [
            "Ran away",
            "Fainted",
            "Jumped into the ocean",
            "Ravaged the city, setting it on fire"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ravaged the city, setting it on fire"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "question": "Who made the bridge across the sea for Rāma and his army to reach Lanka?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Angada",
            "Nala",
            "Neela"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Nala"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "question": "Which of Rāvana’s ministers backed his decision to keep Seetā captive?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "None of the above",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "question": "What was the only boon Vibhishana asked for?",
        "choices": [
            "Immortality",
            "To be very powerful",
            "To remain steadfast in dharma",
            "To be crowned as the king of Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To remain steadfast in dharma"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "question": "Who did Rāma send to Rāvana’s court to give him a last chance to return Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Angada"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Angada"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "question": "Who is said to be a celestial being who had the power to tie down his opponent?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Māreecha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Indrajeet"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "question": "What did Hanuman bring from the Himalayas to revive Rāma and Lakshmana after the Brahmāstra attack?",
        "choices": [
            "A mountain of herbs",
            "A special weapon",
            "A special potion",
            "A divine stone"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A mountain of herbs"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "question": "Who killed Indrajeet?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lakshmana"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "question": "What was Rāvana’s end?",
        "choices": [
            "He was killed by Indrajeet",
            "He was killed by Lakshmana",
            "He was killed by Hanumāna",
            "He was killed by Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was killed by Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "question": "Who did Rāma send to bring Seetā after killing Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vibhishana"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "question": "What did Rāma ask Seetā to do to prove her chastity?",
        "choices": [
            "To touch fire",
            "To swear on her honor",
            "To drink poison",
            "To confess to the rākshasas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To light a pyre"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "question": "Who vouched for Seetā's purity of thoughts and actions?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahma deva",
            "Vishnu",
            "Shiva",
            "Agni deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Agni deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "question": "According to the text, where did the entourage of Rāma arrive after making a stop in Kishkindhā?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Lankā",
            "Prayāg",
            "Chitrakoot"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Prayāg"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "question": "Who was sent by Rāma to inform Bharata of their arrival in Ayodhyā?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the kingdom of Rāma seen as?",
        "choices": [
            "A just kingdom",
            "A kingdom of dharma",
            "A kingdom of righteousness",
            "A kingdom of happiness and prosperity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A kingdom of happiness and prosperity"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "question": "According to the text, who gave shelter to Seetā in his ashram?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Bharadwaja",
            "Rishi Vālmiki",
            "Rishi Agastya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vālmiki"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "question": "According to the text, who is credited with teaching the Ramayana to Lava and Kusha?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Bharadwaja",
            "Rishi Valmiki",
            "Rishi Agastya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Valmiki"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the name of the yajna that Rāma undertook on the advice of his ministers?",
        "choices": [
            "Putreshti yajna",
            "Ashwamedha Yajna",
            "Vishnu Yajna",
            "Brahma Yajna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ashwamedha Yajna"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "question": "Which two brothers moved to the heavenly abode along with Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana and Bharata",
            "Bharata and Sugreeva",
            "Lakshmana and Sugreeva",
            "Bharata and Shatrughna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Bharata and Sugreeva"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "question": "Who stayed back on earth to narrate the story of the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Bharata"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "question": "In the Rāmāyana, what are the purushārthas that are key to living a worthwhile and fruitful life?",
        "choices": [
            "dharma and artha",
            "artha and kāma",
            "dharma, artha, kāma and moksha",
            "dharma and moksha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "dharma, artha, kāma and moksha"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "question": "Which place did Kaikeyi’s parents belong to?",
        "choices": [
            "Videha",
            "Kosala",
            "Kekaya",
            "Lanka"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kekaya"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "question": "According to the text, what were the names of the two most controversial events in the Uttara Kānda?",
        "choices": [
            "The killing of Kumbhakarna and Indrajeet",
            "Rāma’s marriage to Seetā and the killing of Vāli",
            "The abandonment of pregnant Seetā and the killing of Shambuka",
            "The construction of the bridge to Lanka and the war"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The abandonment of pregnant Seetā and the killing of Shambuka"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "question": "What does the text say about Rāma’s understanding of dharma?",
        "choices": [
            "He follows it blindly",
            "He understands it fully",
            "He strives to live by it",
            "He lives it"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He understands it fully"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the objective of the rishis in narrating the lives of ancestors?",
        "choices": [
            "To teach people ethics",
            "To instill fear about their culture",
            "To help people understand their history",
            "To instruct people in the purusharthas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To instruct people in the purusharthas"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "question": "What is the meaning of itihāsa in the context used in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Stories of the past",
            "A mythical story",
            "The history of ancestors",
            "A literary text"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The history of ancestors"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "question": "What did Rāma say about the reason for his decision to accept exile?",
        "choices": [
            "He wanted to prove his father wrong",
            "He wanted to follow his destiny",
            "He wanted to obey his father and his words",
            "He wanted to prove his love for his mother"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He wanted to obey his father and his words"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "question": "What was the name of the city where Seetā was from?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhya",
            "Lanka",
            "Mithilā",
            "Kishkindhā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mithilā"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "question": "What was the name of the bow that Rāma strung and broke in Mithilā?",
        "choices": [
            "Vishnu Dhanush",
            "Shiva Dhanush",
            "Agni Dhanush",
            "Indra Dhanush"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shiva Dhanush"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "question": "According to the text, what were the names of the two royal gurus of Dasharatha?",
        "choices": [
            "Vashishtha and Vālmiki",
            "Vashishtha and Vāmdeva",
            "Vishvamitra and Agastya",
            "Vishvamitra and Vālmiki"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vashishtha and Vāmdeva"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "question": "Where did Bharata choose to live and administer the kingdom from?",
        "choices": [
            "The palace in Ayodhyā",
            "An āshram in Ayodhyā",
            "An āshram in Nandigrām",
            "The forest near Chitrakoot"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "An āshram in Nandigrām"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "question": "How many years of vanvās did Rāma accept from Kaikeyi?",
        "choices": [
            "Ten years",
            "Twelve years",
            "Fourteen years",
            "Sixteen years"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fourteen years"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "question": "What did Bharata place on his head while governing the kingdom?",
        "choices": [
            "The crown",
            "A scepter",
            "Rāma’s sandals",
            "A sword"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma’s sandals"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "question": "Who was the elder brother of Jatāyu?",
        "choices": [
            "Angada",
            "Sampāti",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Vāli"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sampāti"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "question": "Where was Sugreeva given refuge by Rishi Matanga?",
        "choices": [
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Ashoka Vatika",
            "Rishyamukha",
            "Panchavati"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishyamukha"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "question": "What was the name of the bow that Rāma used to kill Māreecha?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Mānavāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mānavāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "question": "What was the name of the celestial weapon that killed Subāhu?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Mānavāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Agneyāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "question": "What was the name of the celestial weapon that killed the rest of the rakshasas with Subāhu and Māreecha?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Mānavāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vayavyāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "question": "Who is said to have been a great admirer of Seetā’s beauty as stated in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Indra",
            "Rāvana",
            "Kuber"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "question": "According to the text, who was referred to as a 'Rājarshi'?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Vishvamitra",
            "Dasharatha",
            "Vāli"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Dasharatha"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "question": "According to the text, who are referred to as the 'five illustrious women' of the Indian epics?",
        "choices": [
            "Seetā, Draupadi, Kunti, Tārā and Mandodari",
            "Ahalyā, Draupadi, Kunti, Tārā and Mandodari",
            "Seetā, Shurpanakha, Kaikeyi, Tārā and Mandodari",
            "Seetā, Draupadi, Kunti, Anjanā and Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ahalyā, Draupadi, Kunti, Tārā and Mandodari"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "question": "What did Brahma deva tell Rishi Vālmiki about the Ramayana’s existence?",
        "choices": [
            "It will only last till the devas’ existence",
            "It will only last till the end of time",
            "It will flourish in the world as long as mountains stand and rivers flow on earth",
            "It will only be remembered by great sages and seers"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It will flourish in the world as long as mountains stand and rivers flow on earth"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "question": "According to the text, which two sons of Dasharatha were twins?",
        "choices": [
            "Rama and Bharata",
            "Bharata and Shatrughna",
            "Lakshmana and Shatrughna",
            "Lava and Kusha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lakshmana and Shatrughna"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "question": "Who was the mother of Bharata?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaushalya",
            "Kaikeyi",
            "Sumitra",
            "Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kaikeyi"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "question": "According to the text, which is the original source of information for the character of Rishi Valmiki?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāmāyana",
            "Mahabharata",
            "Skanda Purāna",
            "Yoga Vashishtha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Skanda Purāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "question": "What does the word 'parākram' mean as mentioned in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Beauty",
            "Charity",
            "Valor",
            "Wisdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Valor"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "question": "Which rishi was referred to as 'the friend of the world' in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Valmiki",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Vashishtha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vishvamitra"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "question": "What does the text mention about the relationship between Vāli and Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "They were enemies",
            "They were distant relatives",
            "They were great friends",
            "They were not on good terms"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They were great friends"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "question": "Who was the mother of Vāli and Sugreeva?",
        "choices": [
            "Rikshārāni",
            "Tārā",
            "Rumā",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "question": "What was the name of Indra’s vāhan (vehicle)?",
        "choices": [
            "Pushpak vimān",
            "Gaja",
            "Garuda",
            "Nandi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Pushpak vimān"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "question": "What was the name of the mountain at the southern coast where Lankā was located?",
        "choices": [
            "Trikuta",
            "Kailash",
            "Suvel",
            "Vindhya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Suvel"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "question": "According to the text, who are the two known for their 'brahma-balam'?",
        "choices": [
            "Vishnu and Shiva",
            "Rāma and Lakshmana",
            "Vashishtha and Vishvāmitra",
            "Brahma deva and Vishnu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vashishtha and Vishvāmitra"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "question": "What was the name of the cow of Rishi Vashishtha?",
        "choices": [
            "Kamadhenu",
            "Shabalā",
            "Nandini",
            "Surabhi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shabalā"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "question": "What did Vashishtha call his cow?",
        "choices": [
            "The wish-fulfilling cow",
            "The power cow",
            "The wonder cow",
            "The gift of the gods"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The wish-fulfilling cow"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "question": "Where was Vāli forbidden to enter by Rishi Matanga?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Lankā",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Rishyamukha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishyamukha"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "question": "What were the names of the two places devastated by the rākshasi Tātakā?",
        "choices": [
            "Malada and Karusha",
            "Ayodhya and Mithilā",
            "Lanka and Kishkindhā",
            "Chitrakoot and Panchavati"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Maladā and Karushā"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "question": "What was the boon that Rāvana’s mother, Kaikasi had?",
        "choices": [
            "She would give birth to extremely powerful sons",
            "Her children would be the most virtuous kings",
            "She would have the blessings of all the gods",
            "She could choose her husband and decide when to give birth"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "She would give birth to extremely powerful sons"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Rāvana seek boons to gain invincibility?",
        "choices": [
            "Kailāsh",
            "Gokarna",
            "Himālayas",
            "In the cave"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Gokarna"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "question": "What did Sugreeva do after being defeated by Vāli?",
        "choices": [
            "He surrendered to Vāli",
            "He challenged Vāli again",
            "He fled to Rishyamukha",
            "He committed suicide"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He fled to Rishyamukha"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "question": "What was the message that Rāvana sent to Kuber?",
        "choices": [
            "To give up Lankā to Rāvana as it belonged to the rākshasas",
            "To be his friend again",
            "To let Rāvana use the Pushpak Vimān",
            "To provide him military strength"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To give up Lankā to Rāvana as it belonged to the rākshasas"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the first one to call Rāma as ‘Gāndharva shreshtha’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Nārada Muni",
            "The people of Ayodhyā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The people of Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the city near the confluence of Ganga and Sarayu?",
        "choices": [
            "Shringaverpur",
            "Panchavati",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Ayodhyā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shringaverpur"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "question": "According to the text, which celestial weapon was used by Rāma to kill Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Shakti",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "question": "What was the meaning of ‘jala dāna’ as mentioned in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "Donating water",
            "Cleaning water",
            "Offering water to deceased ancestors",
            "Purifying water"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Offering water to deceased ancestors"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "question": "Which of Rāvana’s ministers advised him to let go of Seetā and avert a war with Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Prahasta",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Vibhishana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vibhishana"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "question": "Which of these does not apply to what a Brahmarshi represents?",
        "choices": [
            "A king with attributes of a sage",
            "A sage who has realised Brahma",
            "A sage who has mastered senses",
            "A sage who is at the top of the order"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A king with attributes of a sage"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "question": "What does the text state as the meaning of adharma?",
        "choices": [
            "Truth and morality",
            "That which leads to sustainability of society",
            "That which is aligned with one's duty",
            "That which leads to unsustainability and destruction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That which leads to unsustainability and destruction"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the original ancestor of Chandra vamsha (Lunar Dynasty)?",
        "choices": [
            "Manu",
            "Budha",
            "Soma",
            "Vivasvān"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vivasvān"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "question": "Who was the son of Soma?",
        "choices": [
            "Manu",
            "Budha",
            "Ilā",
            "Pururavā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Budha"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the important qualities of the people of Ayodhyā?",
        "choices": [
            "They were wealthy and had everything",
            "They were kind and generous",
            "They were virtuous and self-restrained",
            "They were loyal to their king"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They were virtuous and self-restrained"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "question": "According to the text, who was called ‘Yama’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Vāli",
            "Dharma",
            "Indra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Dharma"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "question": "What does the text state as one of Rāma's qualities with which he conquered the enemy?",
        "choices": [
            "His wisdom",
            "His valour",
            "His compassion",
            "The strength of his bow"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The strength of his bow"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "question": "According to the text, which quality should a king possess to ensure peace and prosperity in the state?",
        "choices": [
            "Strength",
            "Wealth",
            "Righteousness",
            "Generosity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Righteousness"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāma compare Hanumāna to in terms of might?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Vishnu",
            "Vāyu deva",
            "Garuda"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vāyu deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Rāma send Seetā after his concerns about her chastity arose?",
        "choices": [
            "The royal palace",
            "Lanka",
            "The forest near Ganga",
            "The forest near Yamuna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The forest near Ganga"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Lakshmana offer to accompany if Rāma decided to go to vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "Bharata",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Seetā",
            "Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "question": "What did Rāma order Lakshmana to do to Seetā, after hearing of rumours regarding her character?",
        "choices": [
            "To kill her",
            "To send her to Lanka",
            "To send her to forest",
            "To give her back to Janaka"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To send her to forest"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "question": "What was the cause of Rāma's grief, according to the text, after knowing his kingdom's rumour regarding Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "He was worried about Seetā’s safety",
            "He wanted the public to see his authority",
            "He was worried about his reputation",
            "He felt he had made a wrong choice"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was worried about his reputation"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Seetā do after being exiled?",
        "choices": [
            "She fought back",
            "She requested Rāma to get her back",
            "She called upon mother earth to take her back",
            "She started to learn black magic"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "She called upon mother earth to take her back"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "question": "What does the term 'maun vrata' refer to, in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "A fast unto death",
            "A prayer",
            "A vow of silence",
            "A fire ritual"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A vow of silence"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the chief of the vānaras?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Jāmbavana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Vāli"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vāli"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Mantharā say would be the fate of Bharata if Rāma became the king?",
        "choices": [
            "He would become a slave",
            "He would be killed",
            "He would be banished",
            "He would become a non-entity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He would become a non-entity"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Dasharatha say that was the only task left for him to do?",
        "choices": [
            "To lead his army",
            "To build a new city",
            "To find a suitable bride for Bharata",
            "To crown Rāma as the king"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To crown Rāma as the king"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the first one to refer to Rāma as ‘रामो लोकाभिरामो’?",
        "choices": [
            "A citizen of Ayodhyā",
            "A citizen of Mithilā",
            "A citizen of Kishkindha",
            "A citizen of Lanka"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A citizen of Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "question": "According to the text, who was called 'the friend of the world'?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Valmiki",
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Nārada Muni"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vishvamitra"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "question": "What does ‘Nishādarāj’ mean, in the text?",
        "choices": [
            "The king of the forest",
            "The king of Ayodhyā",
            "The king of Nishādas",
            "The king of the demons"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The king of Nishādas"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma give his charioteer as a reward for his work?",
        "choices": [
            "A kingdom",
            "A palace",
            "A thousand cows",
            "Gold coins"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A thousand cows"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "question": "What was the reason Rāma didn’t want to return when Bharata called him?",
        "choices": [
            "He didn't want to rule the kingdom",
            "He was angry with his father",
            "He didn't want to break his promise to his father",
            "He was afraid of facing Kaikeyi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He didn't want to break his promise to his father"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Bharata declare he would do instead of ruling the kingdom?",
        "choices": [
            "He would live in a cave and meditate",
            "He would become a hermit",
            "He would serve the people",
            "He would manage the kingdom as a custodian of Rama"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He would manage the kingdom as a custodian of Rama"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the one who was instrumental in making the people of Ayodhya accept Rāma as their heir?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Bharata",
            "Nārada Muni"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The people of Ayodhya"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "question": "What did Dasharatha request Rāma to do when he informed him of the coronation?",
        "choices": [
            "To listen to his advice",
            "To be humble and alert",
            "To be kind to all citizens",
            "To be a fair ruler"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To be humble and alert"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the first one to convey the news of Rāma’s exile to Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "Hanumāna",
            "Rāma",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Sumantra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "question": "What did Seeta’s father, Janaka say about her?",
        "choices": [
            "She is his most precious jewel",
            "She is a gift from mother Earth",
            "She is his sahadharmacharini",
            "She is his greatest achievement"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "She is his sahadharmacharini"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "question": "What did Seetā use to remove the thorns from her path, when she decided to go with Rāma into the forest?",
        "choices": [
            "Her dress",
            "Her arrows",
            "Her magic",
            "Her hands"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Her hands"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "question": "According to the text, which was the place from where Rāvana abducted Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Panchavati",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Panchavati"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the one quality that Rāma greatly admired in his brother Lakshmana?",
        "choices": [
            "His bravery",
            "His obedience",
            "His intelligence",
            "His unfailing support"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His unfailing support"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "question": "According to the text, who are the ones for whom Rāma is a ‘Gāndharva shreshtha’?",
        "choices": [
            "Those who are skilled in warfare",
            "Those who are skilled in statecraft",
            "Those who are skilled in music",
            "Those who are skilled in music and art"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Those who are skilled in music and art"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "question": "Who was the king of the Nishādas, with whom Rāma was good friends?",
        "choices": [
            "Angada",
            "Guha",
            "Vāli",
            "Sugreeva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Guha"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "question": "What does 'pādukā' mean, according to the text?",
        "choices": [
            "The crown",
            "A royal weapon",
            "Sandals",
            "A signet ring"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sandals"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the meaning of the word 'valmiki'?",
        "choices": [
            "A forest",
            "An anthill",
            "A mountain",
            "A city"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "An anthill"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Bharata do to show his resolve to act as a custodian of Rāma's kingdom?",
        "choices": [
            "He took an oath",
            "He took Rāma’s sandals and carried them on his head",
            "He promised to live an austere life",
            "He agreed to administer the kingdom for 14 years"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He took Rāma’s sandals and carried them on his head"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the aspects that was considered most important in Vālmiki's Rāmāyana?",
        "choices": [
            "The emotions of Rāma",
            "Rāvana's villainy",
            "The brilliance of Rishi Valmiki",
            "Rāma's decision-making"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma's decision-making"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "question": "According to the text, in which part of the Ramayana do the events of Shambuka vadha and the abandonment of Seetā occur?",
        "choices": [
            "Bala Kanda",
            "Yuddha Kanda",
            "Uttara Kanda",
            "Aranya Kanda"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Uttara Kanda"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma not want to be sullied by?",
        "choices": [
            "Personal emotions",
            "Biases",
            "Short-term gratifications",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma say to Lakshmana about the reasons for his decision to accept vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "That they should go against their father's wish",
            "That his decision was based on dharma",
            "That he didn't want to face Kaikeyi",
            "That he did not care about the opinions of others"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That he wanted to obey his father and his words"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "question": "What was the name of the place where Rāma and his people met Rishi Bharadwāja?",
        "choices": [
            "Prayag",
            "Nandigrām",
            "Chitrakoot",
            "Janasthāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Prayag"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the city where Rāma was supposed to be crowned?",
        "choices": [
            "Mithilā",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "question": "According to the text, who advised Rāvana to give up seeking Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Malyavān",
            "Mandodari"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Malyavān"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the wife of Vāli?",
        "choices": [
            "Rumā",
            "Tārā",
            "Anjana",
            "Māndavi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tārā"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "question": "Which of the following is not mentioned as a source of information by the author?",
        "choices": [
            "Valmiki Ramayana",
            "Skanda Purana",
            "Srimad Bhagavad Geeta",
            "Arthashastra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Arthashastra"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "question": "According to the text, what does ‘Brahma-Balam’ refer to?",
        "choices": [
            "The strength of the devas",
            "The physical strength of a Brahmarshi",
            "The mental and spiritual strength of a Brahmarshi",
            "The weapons of a Brahmarshi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The mental and spiritual strength of a Brahmarshi"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the nature of the people of Ayodhyā?",
        "choices": [
            "They were happy and wealthy",
            "They were always singing the glory of Rāma",
            "They were virtuous, strong and content",
            "They were well-mannered, but greedy"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They were virtuous, strong and content"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāma say was ‘like the lord of death himself’?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Rāvana",
            "Māreecha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "question": "According to the text, what was Dasharatha most fearful of?",
        "choices": [
            "Losing his kingdom",
            "Losing his sons",
            "Losing his wealth",
            "Losing his life"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Losing his life"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāma say was capable of reining in the rakshasas?",
        "choices": [
            "Vishvamitra",
            "Vashishtha",
            "Himself",
            "Lakshmana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vishvamitra"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "question": "According to the text, what was Hanumāna well versed in?",
        "choices": [
            "Vedas and Upanishads",
            "Art and music",
            "Politics and warfare",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the last commander of Rāvana killed in the battle?",
        "choices": [
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Makarāksha",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "question": "According to the text, who did the devas ask to test Hanumāna's might?",
        "choices": [
            "Tātakā",
            "Shurpanakhā",
            "Surasā",
            "Lankini"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Surasā"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "question": "According to the text, what was said to be like a sharply turning wheel of fire?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma’s arrow",
            "The power of Vāli",
            "The edge of Rāma's golden bow",
            "The fire around Lakshmana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The edge of Rāma's golden bow"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "question": "Who was the sārthi of Indra who came to help Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Pushpak",
            "Mātāli",
            "Nala",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Mātāli"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the weapon that struck Lakshmana, making him unconscious?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Pāshupatāstra",
            "Shakti",
            "Aindrāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shakti"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the celestial weapon that Rāma used to kill Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra",
            "Brahmāstra",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "question": "Which rishi gave Rāma the powerful and divine weapon used to kill Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Bharadwaja"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Agastya"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Brahma deva praise Seetā for?",
        "choices": [
            "Her wisdom",
            "Her beauty",
            "Her bravery",
            "Her purity and chastity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Her purity and chastity"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "question": "According to the text, who advised Dasharatha to declare Rāma as his successor?",
        "choices": [
            "His ministers",
            "His citizens",
            "His family members",
            "His ministers and citizens"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His ministers and citizens"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "question": "According to the text, who described Rāma as ‘सत्य पराक्रम’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Māreecha",
            "Nārada Muni"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāma described as a person, ‘who is weak cannot ever live peacefully by antagonising the stronger person’?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Vāli",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sugreeva"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "question": "According to the text, what is a ‘kāla chakra’?",
        "choices": [
            "A deadly weapon",
            "The wheel of dharma",
            "The cycle of time",
            "The wheel of destruction"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The wheel of destruction"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the meaning of ‘putra’?",
        "choices": [
            "A son of a king",
            "A virtuous man",
            "One who saves his father from falling into hell",
            "One who has great courage"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "One who saves his father from falling into hell"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the last act of Rāma before he left to Dandakāranya?",
        "choices": [
            "He took a bath in the Ganga",
            "He worshipped his ancestors",
            "He ensured all had been given their dues and responsibilities",
            "He asked for the blessings of his mothers"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He ensured all had been given their dues and responsibilities"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rishis tell Dasharatha about Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "That he was destined to be the king",
            "That he was the most compassionate",
            "That he was exceptionally mature and virtuous",
            "That he was the best warrior ever to be born"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That he was exceptionally mature and virtuous"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rama describe as 'my well-wisher'?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "question": "According to the text, what does Rāma compare himself to when he talks about not being able to win against destiny?",
        "choices": [
            "A river",
            "A mountain",
            "An ocean",
            "A leaf"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A leaf"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "question": "Who does Rāma blame for their separation?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaikeyi",
            "Himself",
            "Fate",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Fate"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these is not a quality that is ascribed to Rāma by others?",
        "choices": [
            "Virtuous",
            "Steadfast",
            "Caring",
            "Envious"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Envious"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "question": "According to the text, who are the ones to follow a virtuous path?",
        "choices": [
            "Only rishis and ascetics",
            "Only kings and ministers",
            "Only Brahmins",
            "Everyone"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Everyone"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "question": "According to the text, who was referred to as ‘Pitāmaha’?",
        "choices": [
            "Shiva",
            "Vishnu",
            "Indra",
            "Brahma deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "question": "According to the text, what does ‘shraddhā’ imply?",
        "choices": [
            "Devotion",
            "Worldview",
            "Faith",
            "Beliefs"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Worldview"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the boon that Brahma deva had given to Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "A boon of invincibility",
            "A boon of strength",
            "A boon of wealth",
            "A boon of near immortality"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A boon of near immortality"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the many reasons why Rāvana wanted to abduct Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "To trouble Rāma",
            "To avenge his sister",
            "He was overcome with her beauty",
            "He had lost his kingdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was overcome with her beauty"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "question": "According to the text, who was known as a great warrior and a great administrator?",
        "choices": [
            "Bharata",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Rāma",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Jatāyu say when he was dying?",
        "choices": [
            "He couldn’t remember the name of the rākshasa",
            "He wasn’t able to give a clue about Rāvana’s location",
            "He was unable to save Seetā",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "question": "According to the text, who was referred to as 'one with a steadfast mind'?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Rāma",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "question": "According to the text, what quality did Vāli have that was described as ‘unmatched’?",
        "choices": [
            "His strength",
            "His wisdom",
            "His fighting spirit",
            "His generosity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His strength"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "question": "According to the text, who was known as ‘the one who made the world cry’?",
        "choices": [
            "Shurpanakhā",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "question": "According to the text, what was Shurpanakha’s true motive for describing Seetā to Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "To make Rāvana help her",
            "To seek revenge on Rāma",
            "To get Rāvana to abduct Seetā",
            "To get Rāvana to fight Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To get Rāvana to abduct Seetā"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "question": "According to the text, who called Rāvana ‘a vile and unrighteous man’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Valmiki",
            "Māreecha",
            "Shurpanakhā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "question": "According to the text, who gave Hanumāna the Pushpak Vimān?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Kuber",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the younger brother of Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Indrajeet",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Aksha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Vibhishana"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these qualities does not apply to a Brahmarshi?",
        "choices": [
            "Control over senses",
            "Transcendence of dualities of sorrow and joy",
            "Knowledge of the Vedas",
            "Expertise in warfare"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Expertise in warfare"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "question": "According to the text, which two places did Seetā mention as being 'known for Rāvana's indulgences'?",
        "choices": [
            "Lankā and Kishkindhā",
            "Ashokavātikā and Dandakaranya",
            "Kailāsh and Ayodhyā",
            "Lankā and Ashokavātikā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Lankā and Ashokavātikā"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "question": "According to the text, why did Rāma call his decision to exile Seetā as ‘a decision made because of destiny’?",
        "choices": [
            "He was giving into destiny",
            "He didn’t have an explanation for why it was happening",
            "He didn’t want to take the decision",
            "He knew Seetā will be back"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He didn’t have an explanation for why it was happening"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "question": "According to the text, who referred to Rāma’s bow as “as big as a rainbow’?",
        "choices": [
            "Vibhishana",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Māreecha",
            "Shurpanakhā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shurpanakhā"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the place where Hanumāna met Seetā in Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "The palace",
            "The jungle",
            "Ashokavātikā",
            "The seashore"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Ashokavātikā"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Lakshmana call Seetā when he suspected that the cries for help were not of Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Cowardly",
            "Uncultured",
            "Dishonest",
            "Foul play"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Foul play"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāvana describe himself to when he was disguised as a rishi?",
        "choices": [
            "The king of Lankā",
            "A friend of Rāma",
            "A traveler",
            "A devotee of Vishnu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A traveler"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the main emotion that Rāma felt while in vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "Sorrow",
            "Grief",
            "Longing for Seeta",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the person who tried to console Seetā after her abduction?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana",
            "Jatāyu",
            "Trijatā",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Trijatā"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Lakshmana and Shatrughna go to spend time with their maternal side?",
        "choices": [
            "Mithilā",
            "Kishkindhā",
            "Kekaya",
            "Lankā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kekaya"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma tell Lakshmana about the reason to respect Brahmāstra?",
        "choices": [
            "To not get killed by the weapon",
            "To maintain the sanctity of the weapon",
            "To not attack his enemy",
            "To learn to use the weapon"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To maintain the sanctity of the Brahmāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Vibhishana insult so that he left Lankā and sought refuge in Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "Indrajeet",
            "Khara",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Tārā say that a person must not do in anger?",
        "choices": [
            "Eat too much",
            "Give up their position",
            "Act recklessly",
            "Seek retribution"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Act recklessly"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma do when he was furious at Varuṇa for not listening to his prayers?",
        "choices": [
            "He cried",
            "He went away",
            "He threatened to dry the ocean",
            "He begged him again"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He threatened to dry the ocean"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "question": "According to the text, how many days did it take to build the bridge across the sea?",
        "choices": [
            "Three",
            "Five",
            "Seven",
            "Nine"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Five"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the mother of Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "Mahātejasvi",
            "Kaikasi",
            "Tārā",
            "Mandodari"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kaikasi"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the meaning of ‘yojana’?",
        "choices": [
            "A mountain",
            "A river",
            "A city",
            "About 8 miles"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "About 8 miles"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "question": "According to the text, which place was also called ‘Suvarnadwipa’?",
        "choices": [
            "Lankā",
            "Bali",
            "Java",
            "Sumatra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Sumatra"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "question": "According to the text, who was 'a strong person with excessive hunger’?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Māreecha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Kumbhakarna"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the minister of Sugreeva who had eightfold cognitive abilities?",
        "choices": [
            "Nala",
            "Neela",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Jāmbavana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the profession of the father of Shravan who was killed by Dasharatha?",
        "choices": [
            "A warrior",
            "A rishi",
            "A tapasvi",
            "A vaidya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A tapasvi"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma say he wanted from the people of Ayodhyā when he accepted vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "Their support",
            "Their faith",
            "Their respect",
            "Their love and affection"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Their faith"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "question": "According to the text, what is ‘Yama-danda’?",
        "choices": [
            "The sword of Yama",
            "The baton of the lord of death",
            "The weapon of Yama",
            "A thunderbolt of Yama"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The baton of the lord of death"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these was not a city in the kingdom of Kosala?",
        "choices": [
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Shringaverpur",
            "Panchavati",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Panchavati"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the nature of Rāvana's city, Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "Peaceful and spiritual",
            "Impoverished and chaotic",
            "A place of luxury and affluence",
            "A humble dwelling"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A place of luxury and affluence"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "question": "According to the text, which place is considered as 'the mouth of the earth'?",
        "choices": [
            "Gangotri",
            "Gomukh",
            "Prayāg",
            "Varanasi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Gomukh"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "question": "What did Dasharatha say he would leave as a legacy for his son?",
        "choices": [
            "His kingdom",
            "His wealth",
            "His values and traditions",
            "A well-protected kingdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A well-protected kingdom"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "question": "According to the text, who is ‘the best of the sages’ who can understand everything?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Vālmiki",
            "Rishi Agastya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vashishtha"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "question": "According to the text, what does the word ‘shloka’ mean?",
        "choices": [
            "A story",
            "A saying",
            "A song",
            "A verse"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A verse"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the one who called Rāma ‘इंद्रोपम’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Sugreeva",
            "A citizen of Ayodhyā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A citizen of Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma’s decision to accept exile signify?",
        "choices": [
            "His anger",
            "His surrender to destiny",
            "His devotion to his father",
            "His indifference to the kingdom"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His devotion to his father"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Indrajeet use to render Rāma and Lakshmana unconscious?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Nāgapāsh",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Nāgapāsh"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the qualities of those who followed Vāli?",
        "choices": [
            "They were fearful of Vāli",
            "They were loyal to Vāli",
            "They were easily manipulated",
            "They were great warriors"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "They were easily manipulated"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Vibhishana tell Rāvana about the consequences of his actions?",
        "choices": [
            "That Rāvana would become immortal",
            "That he was challenging the devas",
            "That he was bringing destruction upon Lankā",
            "That he would lose all his wealth"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That he was bringing destruction upon Lankā"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the place where Tātakā caused devastation?",
        "choices": [
            "Panchavati",
            "Ayodhyā",
            "Maladā and Karushā",
            "Dandakāranya"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Maladā and Karushā"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "question": "According to the text, who did Rāma say were the ‘Lord of Death’?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Rāvana and Kumbhakarna",
            "The rakshasas",
            "Māreecha and Subāhu"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Māreecha and Subāhu"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "question": "According to the text, how many days did it take for Rāma and his group to reach Siddhāshram?",
        "choices": [
            "One day",
            "Two days",
            "Three days",
            "Four days"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Four days"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "question": "According to the text, which river bank did Rāma and Lakshmana stay by during the first night of their exile?",
        "choices": [
            "Sarayu",
            "Gangā",
            "Tamasā",
            "Yamuna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Tamasā"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "question": "According to the text, which of Rāma's relatives were upset by his decision to accept vanvās?",
        "choices": [
            "Only his father",
            "Only his mother",
            "His family and people of Ayodhyā",
            "His brothers"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His family and people of Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Dasharatha order Kaikeyi to be removed from?",
        "choices": [
            "His kingdom",
            "His palace",
            "His household",
            "His presence"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His presence"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the first thing Rāma did after crossing the river Ganga?",
        "choices": [
            "He rested",
            "He looked around",
            "He drank water from the river",
            "He received the knowledge of Bala-Atibalā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He received the knowledge of Bala-Atibalā"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "question": "According to the text, who gave the pushpak vimān to Kuber?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahma deva",
            "Vishnu",
            "Shiva",
            "Indra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Rāvana start to plot to acquire Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "In Lankā",
            "In Janasthāna",
            "In the forest",
            "In the mountains"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In Janasthāna"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "question": "According to the text, how did Jatāyu die?",
        "choices": [
            "He was killed by Rāma",
            "He was killed by Lakshmana",
            "He was fatally injured by Rāvana",
            "He was killed by the rakshasas"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was fatally injured by Rāvana"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "question": "According to the text, what was it that impressed Rāma greatly about Hanumāna?",
        "choices": [
            "His strength",
            "His wisdom",
            "His skill in warfare",
            "His body language"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "His body language"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Lakshmana and Seetā hear Rāma's cry for help?",
        "choices": [
            "In the āshram",
            "By the river",
            "In the forest",
            "On a mountain"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In the āshram"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "question": "According to the text, where did Vāli finally meet his death?",
        "choices": [
            "In the battlefield",
            "In the forest",
            "In his palace",
            "In a mountain pass"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In the forest"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the divine weapon used by Indrajeet to make Rāma and Lakshmana unconscious?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "Nāgapāsh",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahmāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Lakshmana advise Sugreeva when he was overcome by remorse for his misdeeds?",
        "choices": [
            "To meditate",
            "To do penance",
            "To be a better king",
            "To live an austere life"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To be a better king"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Tārā tell Vāli about why he should avoid antagonising Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "She knew they were powerful",
            "She knew they would bring destruction",
            "She knew they were not Vāli's enemies",
            "She knew they were being supported by a powerful person"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "She knew they were being supported by a powerful person"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the cause of the sound that Rāma heard by the Gangā river?",
        "choices": [
            "The sound of celestial beings",
            "The sound of wild animals",
            "The sound of water surging in the river",
            "The sound of the wind blowing in the forest"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The sound of water surging in the river"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the first king to be defeated by Rāvana on his conquest across Bhāratavarsha?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Arjun",
            "Indra",
            "Dasharatha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Arjun"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the cause of the sudden halt of the Pushpak Vimāna for Rāvana in Kailash?",
        "choices": [
            "The power of Shiva",
            "The power of the devas",
            "The curse of Nandi",
            "It got damaged"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The curse of Nandi"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the name of the instrument that Vashishtha used which had great power?",
        "choices": [
            "Dhanush",
            "Bān",
            "Danda",
            "Katar"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Danda"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "question": "According to the text, who said this, ‘You have destroyed this āshram which was so lovingly built by me'?",
        "choices": [
            "Rishi Vishvamitra",
            "Rishi Vashishtha",
            "Rishi Agastya",
            "Rishi Vālmiki"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rishi Vashishtha"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the meaning of ‘agni pariksha’?",
        "choices": [
            "A fire ritual",
            "A fire purification",
            "A test by fire",
            "An oblation to fire"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A test by fire"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the one who first recognized Rāma when he was about to be crowned as prince?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaikeyi",
            "Manthara",
            "Bharata",
            "Nārada Muni"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Nārada Muni"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Brahma deva say about the Ramayana?",
        "choices": [
            "It will be forever remembered by the people of the world",
            "It will be useful in the future",
            "It will teach people to live a happy life",
            "It will flourish in the world as long as the mountains and rivers exist"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It will flourish in the world as long as the mountains and rivers exist"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "question": "According to the text, who had a ‘good control over their senses’?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāvana",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Bharata",
            "Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the purpose for the creation of the artificial heaven by Kaushika?",
        "choices": [
            "To become more powerful",
            "To fulfil the desire of Trishanku",
            "To anger his guru",
            "To attain immortality"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To fulfil the desire of Trishanku"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma say about the importance of fulfilling one's promise?",
        "choices": [
            "It is just an option",
            "It should be avoided, when not suitable",
            "It is an obligation of the king",
            "It is a virtue everyone should abide by"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It is a virtue everyone should abide by"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the nature of Vāli's anger?",
        "choices": [
            "It was controlled",
            "It was always justified",
            "It was always strategic",
            "It was short-tempered and reckless"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "It was short-tempered and reckless"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the meaning of dharma?",
        "choices": [
            "The eternal religion",
            "The law of the land",
            "The principle of righteousness",
            "The principle that leads to sustainability of society"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The principle that leads to sustainability of society"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Tārā say was the correct path for Vāli in his last moments?",
        "choices": [
            "To seek revenge on Sugreeva",
            "To seek revenge on Rāma",
            "To seek peace with Sugreeva and Rāma",
            "To kill Sugreeva and become all powerful"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To seek peace with Sugreeva and Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "question": "According to the text, how many years had Rāma spent in Chitrakoot?",
        "choices": [
            "One month",
            "One year",
            "Two years",
            "Three years"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "One year"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the duties of a king?",
        "choices": [
            "To live a luxurious life",
            "To protect his people",
            "To conquer other kingdoms",
            "To build the biggest palace"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To protect his people"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "question": "According to the text, where did the four brothers of Rāma perform their final rites for their father?",
        "choices": [
            "In Ayodhyā",
            "In the forests",
            "At the banks of the Gangā",
            "At the ashram of Rishi Vashishtha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "In Ayodhyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma consider most important for a king?",
        "choices": [
            "The wealth of the kingdom",
            "The size of the kingdom",
            "The welfare of the citizens",
            "The love and affection of the citizens"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "The welfare of the citizens"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "question": "According to the text, what does ‘yajna vedi’ mean?",
        "choices": [
            "A sacred mountain",
            "A sacred river",
            "A sacred fire altar",
            "A sacred building"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A sacred fire altar"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the one who was ready to break a rule at the first available opportunity?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Krishna",
            "Vibhishana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Krishna"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "question": "According to the text, what is a ‘sārthi’?",
        "choices": [
            "A warrior",
            "A messenger",
            "A charioteer",
            "A spy"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "A charioteer"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the reason that Rāvana did not force himself on Seetā?",
        "choices": [
            "He respected women",
            "He was scared of her curse",
            "He was waiting for her consent",
            "He was not interested in her"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "He was scared of her curse"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the name of the celestial weapon used by Rāma to pierce Rāvana’s chest?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Pāshupatāstra",
            "Agneyāstra",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "question": "According to the text, what was the curse of Nandi on Rāvana?",
        "choices": [
            "He would die a painful death",
            "He would lose his kingdom",
            "He would become immortal",
            "That he would be killed by vānaras"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That he would be killed by vānaras"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "question": "According to the text, where does a rishi seek his strength from?",
        "choices": [
            "From the devas",
            "From the power of mantra",
            "From his innate strength",
            "From the power of nature"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "From his innate strength"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the primary functions of a ‘rishi’?",
        "choices": [
            "To create laws and rules",
            "To teach Vedas and scriptures",
            "To fight wars for the kings",
            "To accumulate wealth"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To teach Vedas and scriptures"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these was not one of the qualities of a good minister?",
        "choices": [
            "Courageous",
            "Incorruptible",
            "Always happy and content",
            "Have expertise in their field"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Always happy and content"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "question": "According to the text, what is the ideal conduct of a good minister?",
        "choices": [
            "Should always agree with the king",
            "Should always seek to please the king",
            "Should give uninhibited opinions in the interest of the kingdom",
            "Should never offer opinions to the king"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Should give uninhibited opinions in the interest of the kingdom"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "question": "According to the text, what was one of the reasons that prompted Rāma to revisit the Rāmāyana?",
        "choices": [
            "To create a more accurate version",
            "To add new characters",
            "To develop a better perspective towards our own lives",
            "To make it more interesting"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To develop a better perspective towards our own lives"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāma say his purpose was in going to Lankā?",
        "choices": [
            "To avenge the death of Jatāyu",
            "To win the war against Rāvana",
            "To save Seetā from her captors",
            "To remove the stigma from his family name"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To remove the stigma from his family name"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "question": "According to the text, who was ‘the one who had the boon to get back whatever she gives away’?",
        "choices": [
            "Menakā",
            "Ahalyā",
            "Shabari",
            "Anusuyā"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Anusuyā"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "question": "According to the text, who was ‘The embodiment of dharma’?",
        "choices": [
            "Krishna",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Rāma",
            "Vibhishana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the ‘most compassionate among the gods’?",
        "choices": [
            "Shiva",
            "Vishnu",
            "Indra",
            "Brahma deva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Shiva"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Rāvana order his sārthi to do when he was unable to defeat Rāma?",
        "choices": [
            "To carry him away from the battlefield",
            "To go back to the palace",
            "To seek help from his ministers",
            "To fight Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "To carry him away from the battlefield"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "question": "According to the text, who is believed to be the most skilled warrior in Rāvana's army?",
        "choices": [
            "Kumbhakarna",
            "Prahasta",
            "Indrajeet",
            "Māreecha"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Indrajeet"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "question": "According to the text, who had the power to tie down the opponent in the war of Rāmāyana?",
        "choices": [
            "Rāma",
            "Lakshmana",
            "Vāli",
            "Indrajeet"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Indrajeet"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Lakshmana use to finally kill Indrajeet?",
        "choices": [
            "Brahmāstra",
            "Pāshupatāstra",
            "Aindrāstra",
            "Vayavyāstra"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Aindrāstra"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "question": "According to the text, what did Hanumāna’s display in Lankā demonstrate?",
        "choices": [
            "That he was a great devotee of Rāma",
            "That he was a loyal servant of Sugreeva",
            "That he was extremely powerful",
            "That his strength is more than that of Rāvana"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "That he was extremely powerful"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "question": "According to the text, which person was described as ‘the heart of dharma’?",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshmana",
            "Vibhishana",
            "Hanumāna",
            "Rāma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rāma"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "question": "According to the text, what does 'moksha' mean?",
        "choices": [
            "Liberation from the cycle of life and death",
            "Righteousness and enterprise",
            "Desire and pleasure",
            "Wealth and prosperity"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Liberation from the cycle of life and death"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "question": "According to the text, who was the queen of Ayodhyā during Rāma’s exile?",
        "choices": [
            "Kaushalyā",
            "Seetā",
            "Kaikeyi",
            "There was no queen"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "There was no queen"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "question": "According to the text, who gave the boon of making Rāvana near immortal?",
        "choices": [
            "Indra",
            "Vishnu",
            "Brahma deva",
            "Shiva"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brahma deva"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "question": "According to the text, which of these was not an intended quality of the people of Rāma's kingdom?",
        "choices": [
            "Contented",
            "Healthy",
            "Righteous",
            "Rich"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rich"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "question": "According to the text, who was described as the most learned among all the vānaras?",
        "choices": [
            "Vāli",
            "Sugreeva",
            "Jāmbavana",
            "Hanumāna"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hanumāna"
    }
]